A Guide to Materials on Women
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Dixon Family Papers 1826-1836, 22 items.
  Letters from Ann F. Rootes (Mrs. William Garret) Minor of Fredericksburg, Virginia, to Harriet P. Dixon (Mrs. Jacob Sheldon) of Gloucester County. A delightful set of letters that chronicals two young ladies growing up in Virginia. The letters discuss parties, romance, daily life and society. #38-464
- Douglas Family Papers 1731-1900, ca. 100 items.
  Papers of the Douglas family of Green County, Virginia, containing land and property sales, bankruptcy petitions, wills and letters. In October 1864, Maggie Douglas writes from Dayton, Virginia, to her mother and brother in Greene County, Virginia, concerning the looting and burning of her home by the Union army. Families for miles around have had their property destroyed. After the war, the Douglas family suffered increased financial difficulties and in December of 1873, John Douglas files for bankruptcy. Maggie moves to Georgia soon after the Civil War. Life does not get much better as much as their property is again destroyed by fire and her husband suffers a nervous breakdown. #702
- Douglas Family Papers 1817-1903, 660 items.
  Papers of the Douglas and Terrell families of Lynchburg and Cumberland County, Virginia, chiefly letters to Mary Jane Douglas, 1817-1903 from various female relatives. a very strong collection of correspondence between women, two items of note include a letter dated March 1, 1849, Virginia Ward of Leaksville writes of the murder of 2 children, 1 white and 1 black, by a negro girl. No motivation was given. In another letter, October 30, 1850, Jennie Ward writes to Mary Douglas, of an aunt who gives birth the same day her husband dies. #3108 and 3118
- Douglas(s) Family Papers 1728-1899, 700 items.
  The paper of William Douglass of Loudoun County, Virginia, as well as General Hugh Douglas, and Colonel Charles Douglas. Items of note are many 18th indentures involving women as well as a couple of wills. There is also the 19th century correspondence, accounts and receipts of Miss Mary Ross. #2981
- Draper Family Narrative ca. 1825, 1 volume
  A manuscript narrative of the Ingles and Draper families, early settlers in western Virginia, by John Ingles (d. 1836). The narrative has been published as Escape from Indian Captivity: The Story of Mary Draper Ingles and Son Thomas Ingles. #38-246
- Drawings 1935, 65 items.
  Hand-colored copies by Sonia Tregaskis of drawings made, ca. 1585-1587, by John White of American Indians, flora, fauna, etc. The original drawings are in the British Library. A second set of copies is in the Clements Library, Ann Arbor, Michigan. #38-762
- Drawings and Paintings 1809-1890, 3 items.
  Pencil drawing of a woman from original designs by Tinelli, Rome, 1809. Watercolor of peasant woman with jugs, signed Heller, 1890. #8925-a
- Louise Driscoll Papers 1931-32., 7 items.
  Poems and correspondence between Louise Driscoll and Sybil Gow Johnston. They shared poetry and critiqued each others' work. #38-429-a
- Nellie Porterfield Dunn 1897-1938
  Letters to and from Nellie Porterfield (Mrs. John H.) Dunn regarding her sketch and portrait of Percy B. Shelley by the American artist, William E. West. The main body of correspondence is with Mrs. A. P. Bryant, niece of the artist West, R. U. Johnson, associate editor of Century Magazine; r. W. Gilder, editor of Century Magazine, Henry S. Salt, and Richard Garnett. #38-177
- Martha Tabb Dyer Diaries 1823-1839, 3 items.
  Three diaries, 1823-39, kept by this Calloway County, Missouri, woman with references to sewing, etc., for her slaves. #7776
- Eddins Family Papers 1847-1863, 35 items.
  Letters and records of members of the Eddins family of King George County, Madison, and Richmond, Virginia. Several Civil War letters deal with the Peninsula Campaign and the California Gold Rush. There are some letters (1850) from a young lady attending an unidentified girls school (possibly Piedmont) writing about her music program and a letter dated November 20, 1858 from Betsy Brock to her cousin Mary telling her of how "Julia Ann" (possibly a slave?)was taken from them by a Mr. Burton with the knowledge of Betsy's mother. Other female correspondence is scattered throughout the collection. #1469
- Edgehill School for Girls 1864, 2 items.
  Two letters, January 10 and April 16, 1864, from a Nellie W. to her cousin Bettie. Topics touched are social activities, and the "Yankees" coming very close to the area. #38-421
- Edgehill Randolph Papers 1732-1861, ca. 1100 items.
  The papers of the Randolph family of "Edgehill," Albemarle County, Virginia, and those of the allied Nicholas and Jefferson families including an exchange of correspondence between Martha Jefferson and her friends regarding Jefferson's voyage to France. See related 5533. #1397
- Antoinette Edmunson Poetry 1908-1920, 2 items
  Manuscript volume of her poems, and two other poems. #3192, -a
- Emmanuel Episcopal Church Papers 1871-1983, 15 items.
  The collection of a genealogical study entitled The papers of Louisa Emmerson is an account of Louisa Emmerson of Portsmouth, Virginia and her ancestors and descendants (with photographs). #2267
- Emmerson Family Papers 1824-1866, 8 items.
  Of interest is the diary of Nancy Emmerson, sister-in-law of Catherine Emmerson, wife of the Reverend Luther Emmerson, kept at Middlebrook, Augusta County, Virginia. The diary covers the years 1862-1864; she makes comments on the war conducted in the Shenandoah Valley, justness of slavery, local troops and her own bout with illness. #9381
- Enchanted Years Manuscripts 1919-1921, 160 items.
  This collection of 160 items, letters and poems, 1919-1921, concern the publication of The Enchanted Years, a book of contemporary verse dedicated by poets of Great Britain and the U. S. to the University of Virginia on the occasion of its 100th anniversary. Women include: H.D., Josephine Dodge Bacon, Katharine Lee Bates, Frances Neil Benet, Anna H. Branch, Amelia Burr, Sarah Norcliffe Cleghorn, Helen Gray Cone, Grace Conkling, Eleanor Rogers Cox, Agnes Rand Lee, Amy Lowell, Corinne Roosevelt Robinson, Sara Teasdale, Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy, and many others. #38-429
- Rosalie Caden Evans Papers 1918-1948, ca. 3500 items.
  Letters of Rosalie Caden Evans and Daisy Caden Pettus concerning Mrs. Evans' experiences in Mexico during the Agrarian Revolution. Correspondence concerns settlements of her estate and publication of her letters. Additional papers are in regards to the settlement of Mrs. Evans' Mexican estate, including Mexican and United States legal documents, maps, and correspondence. Daisy Caden Pettus and her attorneys attempted to gain compensation for Mrs. Evans' lands which were seized by the Agrarians after they murdered Mrs. Evans. See Claude Philippe Dussaud's 1990 University of Virginia Masters Thesis, Agrarian Politics, Violence, and the Struggle for Social Control in Pueblo from 1918 to 1927: The Case of Rosalie Evans. #2895, etc.
- Fauquier Female Institute 1889, 1 item.
  Program for final exercises at Fauquier's Female Institute, June 13, 1889. #370.
- Jane E. Ferguson Letter 1824, 1 item.
  Letter, November 8, 1824, to her father, James B. Ferguson, describing Lafayette's visit to Monticello and the University of Virginia. "Hundreds of ladies welcomed him [Lafayette] by waving their handkerchiefs." #38-122-a
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife Papers 1861-1972, 22 items.
  Three notebooks and loose papers, kept by Fife, while a student at Albemarle Female Institute, who later became the wife of Robert Hendon Fife. Of interest is a baby journal kept by Fife, 1869, for her son Howell, who died in infancy. #5633-b
- Esther Finger Autograph Book 1883, 1 item.
  Autograph book of Esther Finger (?) written in German (?). #2911
- Fitzhugh and Marye Papers 1830's, 1860's, 5 items.
  Items from the law offices of Fitzhugh and Marye. Item of particular interest is an inventory of Mrs. Charlotte Thornton's slaves, primarily women. One comment is "Willy, a young woman, about 17 yrs old, healthy and strong, well formed, but rather a homely face." #2062
- Walter Fontaine Papers ca. 1810-1910, ca. 200 items.
  Mainly legal and business papers of this Buckingham County, Virginia merchant. Included is a deed of sale. December 1822, for a female slave and her two children. #7984
- Margaret Freeman Letter 1870, 1 item.
  Letter, August 1, 1870, Margaret Freeman to W. Torrey concerning Mr. Torrey's new book, her father, and churches in France. Found in a book from the library of Mr. Torrey. #3453
- Margaret Funkhauser Forbes Collection ca. 1938-1979, 13 items.
  The collection contains eights five-year diaries, three travel diaries, a set of Iranian picture cards and a bibliography of references to Thomas Fortune Ryan. The travel diaries describe trips to Italy in 1961, Greece in 1967, and Iran in 1974. Their personal diaries record Forbes family daily activities, social life, trips, weather, and children's development. #9231-z
- James Westphal Ford Papers 1773-1877, 15 items.
  Business and legal papers of Mathews County, Virginia merchant and planter. Included is an account, 1835-1843, of Miss Ann Weston with Jarvis Barnum, for various types of sewing material and other sundry items. Also, an account, 1857-1858, of Miss Mary F. Wright with Leonidas James, for personal items. #3523
- Franklin Female Seminary Papers 1911-1913, 35 items.
  Miscellaneous papers concerning the Franklin Female Seminary in Southampton County, Virginia, all financial, legal or fiscal in nature. Included are ledgers, a checkbook, receipts, and legal papers concerning the dissolution of the school. #38-606
- Fugitive Verse n.d.
  The poetry and verse of Annie Duncan Cox, Inez May Cox, Josephine Rinckney, Lucy N. Randolph, Katherine K. Rocker and Helen Harriett Salls. #38-625
- Roberta Tayloe Fuller Memoir 1920's-1940's, 1983, 1 volume.
  A 247-page memoir detailing Fuller's childhood at "Powhatan," King George County, Virginia. Highlights are her family, farming, nursing training at Garfield Hospital, Sloan Medical Center in New York City, and being a member of the Army Nurse Corps during World War II in England, North Africa, and Italy. #38-62-b
- Mrs. J. H. Fultz Letters 1826-1950, ca. 50 items.
  Includes letters, 1875-1876, from Mrs. Fultz to Washington May regarding money for Leanna (a freed woman) and her child. #8850
- Gaines Family Papers 1810-1905, ca. 1700 items.
  Papers, correspondence, and records of the Gaines family of "Do Well," Saxe, Virginia, consisting principally of papers of Richard Venable Gaines and his son Richard H. Gaines, with ca. 100 letters of Mr. and Mrs. R. V. Gaines concerning the Grange (1824), the University of Virginia, and family matters. There is a manuscript music book, ca. 1856, kept by Sarah Stith. There are letters to R. H. Gaines from his wife, Jeanie, his mother, E. M. Gaines, and his sisters Mattie, Bessie, and Minnie Gaines throughout the collection. Other correspondents include Caroline Davis, Fanny Pryor, Sally Carter, Alice W. Robertson, Mary C. Robertson, and Mary McDonald. #3596
- Gaines Family Papers 1841-[1890?], 69 items.
  Chiefly the correspondence of Marcus Junius Gaines (1821- ), Maggie Dickson Gaines (1831- ), and other members of the Gaines family of Dinwiddie County, Virginia, and include typed transcripts for most of the letters. Marcus Gaines was the United States Consul to Tripoli from 1849-186[8?], where he met and married his English wife, Maggie Dickson, in 1854. Included are the following topics: Marcus and Sally Gaines' recent profession of faith (November 30, 1841); Sally to Tom Gaines concerning his recent conversion (December 3, 1850); a Josiah Moore letter concerning the death of Mary Ann Camm Gaines, the mother of Marcus Gaines, (April 22, 1871); and an eulogy or obituary for Mary Ann Camm Gaines (April 7, 1871). #10716
- Thomas Garland Papers 1820-1870, 1500 items.
  Financial and business papers of Thomas Garland of Charlottesville, Virginia. Correspondence with family in Richmond, Virginia, discusses local politics, economic matters, and the Civil War in Virginia. Thomas Garland purportedly lived with or possibly married a Black woman (by whom he had children) after his wife, Jane Taylor Garland, left him at the beginning of the War. Documents to substantiate this story include a letter, March 11, 1861, from Jane Garland to "Mr. Garland" requesting support; and letters to "Mother or Mama" in the 1870's and 1890's (when Jane Taylor Garland would be dead or at the least past child bearing age). A collection which deserves more attention. #2020
- James Mercer Garnet Papers 1840-1916, ca. 200 items.
  Papers of the James Mercer Garnett family of Baltimore, Virginia. The elder Garnett was a professor at the University of Virginia from 1882-1896, his son was secretary of the Maryland chapter of the University of Virginia Alumni Association, and his wife active in the Daughters of the Confederacy, a predecessor of the United Daughters of the Confederacy. Mrs. Garnett seems to have been an important officer in this organization and her records are fairly complete. There are also short sketches written by Mrs. Garnett of missionary work done by a Baltimore Church in the Far East. #1719
- Charles Danna Gibson Sketchbook 1884, 1 item.
  Sketchbook, December 30, 1884, of various people, including caricatures of women. There is also a newspaper clipping about Mrs. Charles Dana Gibson, the former Miss Irene Langhorne. #3625
- Gilliam Family Papers 1802 (1823-1932), 1500 items.
  The legal, financial and personal papers of the Gilliam family of Dinwiddie County, Virginia, especially John Gilliam, his wife Mary Eppes Gilliam and their four children. Upon John Gilliam's death, his wife Mary Eppes Gilliam carried on the family affairs and her name appears frequently in accounts and correspondence during the 1850's and 1860's. However, there is little material concerning the Civil War. There is also material pertaining to Rosa Boisseau, a cousin of the Gilliams, about whom little is known. The primary interest of this collection is its strong records regarding slave trading, hiring, and selling. #2608
- Gilliam Family Papers 1794-1913, ca. 40 items.
  Items relating to the Gilliam family of Dinwiddie County, Virginia. Of note are legal documents concerning Mary Gilliam (1840-1860). #3164
- Gilliam Family Papers 1834-1905, ca. 77 items.
  Papers of the Gilliam family of Petersburg, Virginia, including correspondence of John W. Gilliam, Joseph P. Gilliam, Mary E. C. Gilliam, Samuel Y. Gilliam, and Susan Gilliam. Included is a letter, 1854, from Mary E. C. Gilliam to Cadet Joseph P. Gilliam; a Guardian Account, 1867-1870, for Mary E. C. Gilliam; and, a funeral notice, June 17, n.y., for Mary E. C. Gilliam. #3593, -a
- Gooch Family Papers ca. 1800-1890, ca. 1800 items.
  Correspondence and papers of Col. Claiborne William Gooch of Richmond, Virginia, his wife Rebecca, and sons Richard Barnes, Philip, and Arthur Fleming. The collection is primarily political in nature with much material on the United States Bank, nullification, and states rights. #3921, -a
- Armistead Churchill Gordon Papers 1887-1922, ca. 2000 items.
  Papers of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Rector of the University of Virginia, concerning policies and activities of the Board of Visitors, primarily from 1894-1898 and 1906-1918. Included are Women's College proposals. Highlights are annex system (1894), coordination scheme, backed by the Virginia Federation of Women's Colleges, fight in legislature on coordinate scheme and women in summer school. #38-145
- Gorges Family Papers 1550-1930, ca. 4000 items.
  Material gathered by Raymond Gorges for his work on the Gorges family who have played a significant part in the intellectual, and political life of Great Britain and Ireland. Documents include marriage contracts, wills, legal documents, and two letters to Mrs. Frances Gorges from the Duke of Wellington. #1641, 1686, 1740, 1759, 1781
- Bettie Ann Graham Collection 1860-1862, 2 items.
  The diary of Bettie Ann Graham recounts, somewhat sporadically, the years 1860-1862, during which time she was a schoolgirl in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and at home in Wythe County, Virginia. The diary gives a telling account of the girl's daily life in Philadelphia, but its primary value lies in the fat that it reveals how ine girl's thoughts and feelings were affected by the outbreak of the Civil War. Accompanying the diary are some biographical notes on Miss Graham's family and the family of John Robinson, whom she married. #10234
- Lucy G. Gratton 1827-1832, 1 album
  Scrapbook kept by Lucy Gratton, consisting chiefly of hand-written copies of poems. #1885
- Graves Family Papers ca. 1820's-1880's, 58 items.
  Primarily the financial papers of General Brazillai Graves of Randolph County, Georgia, who attended the University of Virginia in 1823. Documents are from Alabama, Georgia, North Carolina and Virginia. Letter dated January 14, 1828, Mary Graves to her husband Brazillai Graves, is an intimate love letter, and letter from Mary Anne of Pleasant Grove, Alabama, to Sarah of Danville, Virginia, n.d. (probably post Civil War) tells of local courtship and "boy talk" in general. #1776
- Margaret Gray Papers 1914-1970, 77 items.
  Includes letters, a diary, and a copy of A short sketch of the lives of Jean Pierre Sioussat and Charlotte Julia deGraf his wife. The letters are chiefly those of Arthur Bowers, Liverpool, England, to Margaret Gray. The diary, 1914, of Miss Gray, describes a voyage to England. #5323-b
- Millie Richards Stone Gray 1822-1829, 1 item
  A diary for the period January 1, 1822 through May 21, 1829, kept by Millie Richards Stone (Rowe?) Gray (1800- ), married to William Fairfax Gray. The diary is elegant in style and rich in the detail of daily social life and customs of Fredericksburg. Each entry usually includes a note of the day's weather, and among the last pages are some household accounts and inventories, and recipes. #1709
- Great Britain Press Bureau Photographs 1914-1918, ca. 1940 items.
  Official photographs issued by the Press Bureau. Among the subjects included is women's roles. #3067
- Green Family Papers 1859-1904, 40 items.
  Of interest are the letters of Emmie Holmes to Lizzie Green, from Georgia and North Carolina. These letters include discussion of the war and a great support of the Confederacy. #6211.
- Louise Greer Papers 1936-1965, 82 items.
  The papers contain correspondence, 1961-1965, of Greer (1899-1966) with several libraries owning Edgar Allan Poe and Henry Wadsworth Longfellow letters, student essays on Poe by Greer and Charles Aycock, notes on published Poe biographies, and photographs, postcards and souvenirs of Poe and Poe associated places. #3565-b
- Elizabeth Fenner Gresham 1936-1939, 5 items.
  Papers of the Charlottesville actress and playwright. Included are typescripts of three comedy-dramas by Gresham: The whetstone, rewritten as Women, with a difference, and That lesser Aphrodite. In addition there is a typescript copy of "Death takes a holiday" by Walter Ferris, with Gresham's acting "sides" containing stage directions: and portions of the script for Edgar Allan Poe's Politician. #6679-e
- Grinnan Family Papers 1740-1935, ca. 5500 items.
  Papers of the Bryan, Tucker, and Grinnan families of Virginia. Numerous correspondent are women, including Frances Bland Coalter, Elizabeth Tucker Coalter Bryan, Cornelia Grinnan, Nina Stuart Grinnan, Georgia Screven Bryan, and Helen Grinnan. There are also documents relating to Brampton Home School for Young Ladies. #49
- Grinnan Family Papers 1800-1940, 1800 items.
  Papers of Reverend Randolph Bryan Grinnan and related families of Bryan, Coalter, and Glaspell. Highlights include life at Randolph Macon College in the 1930's: the independent Coalition of American Women's campaign against the New Deal and for Alf Landon; an 1867 marriage certificate for Lucy and Abram Carter, a Black couple; correspondence of women, including Elizabeth Tucker Coalter Bryan, Georgia Screven Bryan, Eudora Glassell, Cornelia Grinnan, Wllia Grinnan, Georgia Bryan Grinnan, and several others; sketches by Georgia Bryant Grinnan (1897); and a recipe book brought to "Brampton" by Georgia Screven Bryan when she married Andrew Glassell Grinnan in 1859. #2118-a-b
- Doris Grumbach Papers 1939-1984, 6295 items.
  Manuscripts, correspondence, reviews, articles, speeches, cassette tapes and newsclippings, and manuscripts or published copies of over 300 reviews by Grumbach and about 85 articles and speeches by her as well as interviews with Ann Beattie, Kay Boyle, Charles Davis, Gilbert Harrison, Abigail McCarthy, Mary McCarthy, Rod MacLeish, Larry McMurtry, William McPherson and Sally Quinn. Correspondence is both personal and professional and concerns the writing of novels and reviews, teaching at the College of Saint Rose and American University, literary editorship of The New Republic, 1970-1975, professional associations, various conferences and workshops, and literary awards. Topics in both her writing and correspondence include feminist literature, small press publications, contemporary literature, book reviewing for periodicals and public radio, college education, the development of young writers, editing and publication, the artist colonies at McDowell and Yaddo, and the Catholic Church. #10585.
- Sallie Gwathmey Postcards n.d., 5 items.
  Postcards from Mrs. A. R. I., "Retreat," Richmond, Virginia, to Sallie Gwathmey, Evington, Campbell County, Virginia, on personal topics. Appear to be of the late nineteenth century. #38-238
- Annette F. Van Winkle Hale Papers 1929, ca. 25 items.
  Her papers in regards to the dedication of the Lafayette Room in Pavilion VI, East Lawn, University of Virginia. #2792-d
- Nancy Hale Papers 1930-1955, ca. 5,400 items.
  Notes, drafts, manuscripts, and gallery proofs of Hale's short stories and novels The Prodigal Women and The Sign of Jonah, along with correspondence with publishers and literary agent Elizabeth Nowell, and related material. There are also letters concerning Elinor Wyllie and copies of Wyllie letters. #3646, a-h
- Florence Gardiner Hall Papers 1935, 1944, 3 items.
  Letters to Mrs. Florence Gardiner Hall from General John T. Pershing, with a photograph of Captain and Mrs. [Margaret Jane] Pershing in Japan, 1905. There is also a newspaper clipping, May 1944, re the decorating of Mrs. Hall, of New Lebanon, by Queen Elizabeth of Belgium, at the Pershing Chateau, for her work with YMCA-AEF, 1918-1919. #3529
- Florence Gardiner Hall Papers 1904-1945, 12 items.
  Letter, April 20, 1904, from Tokyo Shimidyu, Kujimechi, Japan; letter, August 14, 1920, from Mabel Davison: two letters, June 18 and October 14, 1928, from Fanny MacVeagh, Tokyo; extract of letter by Pierre Bertagne; copy of letter, April 23, 1945, of Chaplain Paul van K. Thompson describing invasion of Okinawa; two invitations from American Embassy, Tokyo; two invitations from Japanese Imperial Family; and two clippings of the wedding of Reinetta Plimpton and William Stanwood Pier, 1940. #3629
- Hamlet Family Papers 1807-1889, 26 items.
  Miscellaneous papers of the Hamlet family of Campbell County, Virginia. Items of note include two documents pertain to two black women and their standing in the Union Hill Baptist Church. #3270-b
- Harrison Family Papers 1720-1960, ca. 1000 items.